<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7911 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7911.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-idr-addpath-paths-limit-00" ipr="trust200902" consensus="true" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.8 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Paths Limit for Multiple Paths in BGP">Paths Limit for Multiple Paths in BGP</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-idr-addpath-paths-limit-00"/>
    <author fullname="Donatas Abraitis" surname="Abraitis">
      <organization>NetDef</organization>
      <address>
        <email>donatas@opensourcerouting.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Alvaro Retana" surname="Retana">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>aretana@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jeffrey Haas" surname="Haas">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jhaas@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <keyword>template</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies a BGP extension enabling the receiver to
        communicate the sender about the path limit for multiple paths
        related to a specific address prefix, thereby optimizing the
        transmission by selectively relaying pertinent path information
        instead of the entire set of known paths.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The BGP specification <xref target="RFC7911"/> defines a BGP extension
        that allows the advertisement of multiple paths for the same address
        prefix without the new paths implicitly replacing any previous ones.
      </t>
      <t>
        Multiple paths for a large number of prefixes may be received by a BGP
        speaker, potentially depleting memory resources or even causing
        network-wide instability, which can be considered a denial-of-service
        attack.
      </t>
      <t>
        Without knowing the path limit the receiver is capable of accepting,
        we can't tell the sender to send an arbitrary number of paths for the
        same prefix. Without this information, the sender can send as many paths
        as it wants.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a BGP extension that allows the receiver to inform
        the sender of the path limit of multiple paths for the same address
        prefix instead of sending all known paths.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="simple_list">
      <name>Specification of Requirements</name>
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
        they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Paths Limit capability</name>
      <t>
        The ADD-PATH Capability <xref target="RFC7911"/> value field consists
        of one or more of the following tuples:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="addpath_capability">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Address Family Identifier (2 octets)           |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Subsequent Address Family Identifier (1 octet) |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Send/Receive (1 octet)                         |
    +------------------------------------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        This format is strictly defined, and by adding a new field “Paths Limit”,
        after Send/Receive flags, the format can't be changed in a
        backward-compatible way.
      </t>
      <t>
        Hence, we define a new BGP capability with Capability Code TBD.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Capability Value field consists of one or more of the following
        tuples:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="paths_limit_capability">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Address Family Identifier (2 octets)           |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Subsequent Address Family Identifier (1 octet) |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Paths Limit (2 octet)                          |
    +------------------------------------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        A BGP speaker who wishes to indicate support for multiple AFI/SAFIs MUST
        do so by including the information in a single instance of the
        PATHS-LIMIT capability.
      </t>
      <t>
        This new PATHS-LIMIT capability MUST be used only with ADD-PATH capability.
        If PATHS-LIMIT capability is received, but no ADD-PATH capability, then
        PATHS-LIMIT capability MUST be ignored.
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Paths Limit: this field indicates the maximum paths limit the receiver
          is able to receive from its peer. If the Paths Limit is received as zero (0),
          the capability SHOULD be ignored.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        If both ADD-PATH capability, and PATHS-LIMIT are negotiated, but PATHS-LIMIT
        capability is empty (no per AFI/SAFI limits defined), the capability SHOULD be
        ignored.
      </t>
      <t>
        Paths limit is defined as 2 octets to avoid being too small for some specific
        use cases, like huge ECMP fabrics. But a typical use case would be on the order
        of between 2 and 8.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Operation</name>
      <t>
        For a BGP speaker to be able to send paths limit to its peer, that BGP speaker
        MUST advertise the PATHS-PATH Capability and specify the Paths Limit count is
        willing to receive.
      </t>
      <t>
        PATHS-LIMIT capability MUST be advertised only if ADD-PATH capability is
        supported by the sender.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the sender wants to advertise multiple paths for the same prefix, and
        PATHS-LIMIT capability is advertised, and received, then the sender MUST
        respect this paths limit and send only the specified maximum number of paths
        per prefix instead of sending all known paths or as many as the sender wants.
      </t>
      <t>
        A BGP speaker SHOULD include the best route <xref target="RFC4271"/> when more
        than one path is advertised to a neighbor unless it is a path received from
        that neighbor.
      </t>
      <t>
        Usually, some implementations provide a few options to either send all known
        paths or send N best paths.
        The receiving implementation SHOULD provide a configuration knob to specify
        the maximum number of paths to accept from the sender for multipath prefixes.
        If for example, the receiver advertises paths limit as 2, but the sender has
        6 paths to send, it MUST send only 2 best paths.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        IANA has assigned the value TBD for the PATHS-LIMIT Capability
        described in this document.  This registration is in the
        "Capability Codes" registry.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references title="Normative References">
        &RFC2119;
        &RFC4271;
        &RFC7911;
        &RFC8174;
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
