<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-abraitis-idr-maximum-prefix-orf-00" ipr="trust200902" consensus="true" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.8 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Maximum Prefix Outbound Route Filter for BGP">Maximum Prefix Outbound Route Filter for BGP</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-abraitis-idr-maximum-prefix-limit-orf"/>
    <author fullname="Donatas Abraitis" surname="Abraitis">
      <organization>NetDef</organization>
      <address>
        <email>donatas@opensourcerouting.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Inter-Domain Routing</workgroup>
    <keyword>BGP MAXIMUM PREFIX ORF</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document introduces a Maximum Prefix ORF (Outbound Route Filtering) type for BGP.
        It aims to provide a mechanism whereby the sender of route information is informed of
        the maximum number of prefixes that the receiver is willing to accept. This facilitates
        improved resource management by limiting the number of routes exchanged, avoiding
        unnecessary or excessive route propagation, and reducing memory and CPU load.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The Outbound Route Filtering (ORF) capability, as defined in <xref target="RFC5291"/>, provides
        a mechanism for a BGP speaker to send to its BGP peer a set of Outbound Route Filters that can be
        used by its peer to filter outbound routing updates to the speaker.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a new ORF type, called "Maximum Prefix Outbound Route Filter", which enables
        a BGP receiver to specify the maximum number of prefixes that a sender should transmit. Rather than
        specifying particular prefixes, the Maximum Prefix ORF allows the receiver to define a threshold for
        the number of prefixes it is willing to accept, regardless of specific prefix ranges.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Maximum Prefix ORF provides an efficient mechanism for managing resource consumption, particularly
        in large BGP environments, by enabling a BGP speaker to limit the number of routes it propagates based
        on the preferences of its peer.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Efficiency</name>
      <t>
        The Maximum Prefix ORF provides significant operational efficiency by reducing unnecessary BGP UPDATE
        messages between peers. Without this ORF, all available routes are sent to the receiver, which must then
        filter and limit the number of prefixes it installs in its BGP table. Although the receiver filters routes
        upon receipt, it still processes each incoming UPDATE, resulting in increased CPU and memory load,
        especially in large networks.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Operation</name>
      <t>
        The Maximum Prefix ORF is designed to work in conjunction with existing maximum prefix filtering mechanisms,
        such as configuration commands like "neighbor X maximum-prefix N".
        This configuration allows operators to set a maximum prefix limit for a BGP neighbor.
      </t>
      <t>
        With the addition of the Maximum Prefix ORF, the receiver can proactively communicate this limit to its BGP peer,
        informing the sender to enforce the same maximum prefix constraint. This ORF type is sent from the receiver to the
        sender and allows the sender to filter updates before they are sent, aligning with the receiver's specified limit.
      </t>
      <t>
        Upon receiving the Maximum Prefix ORF, the sender MUST ensure that the total number of prefixes in outbound updates
        to this receiver does not exceed the specified limit. Any prefixes beyond this limit are filtered by the sender,
        reducing the load on the receiver's BGP processing and eliminating unnecessary UPDATE messages.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="simple_list">
      <name>Specification of Requirements</name>
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
        they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Maximum Prefix ORF-Type</name>
      <t>
        The value of the ORF-Type for the Maximum Prefix ORF-Type is TBD.
      </t>
      <t>
        A Maximum Prefix ORF entry is encoded as defined in the table.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="maximum_prefix_orf">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Address Family Identifier (2 octets)           |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Subsequent Address Family Identifier (1 octet) |
    +------------------------------------------------+
    | Prefix Limit (4 octets)                        |
    +------------------------------------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        The meaning and use of the fields are as follows:
      </t>
      <ul empty="true">
       <li>
       <dl newline="true">
        <dt>Address Family Identifier (AFI):</dt>
        <dd>This field is the same as the one used in <xref target="RFC4760"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Subsequent Address Family Identifier (SAFI):</dt>
        <dd>This field is the same as the one used in <xref target="RFC4760"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Prefix Limit:</dt>
        <dd>This field indicates the maximum prefix limit the receiver
        wants to receive from its peer. If the received Prefix Limit is
        zero (0), the tuple SHOULD be ignored.</dd>
       </dl>
       </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <table anchor="table_ex">
        <name>BGP Outbound Route Filtering (ORF) Types</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center">Value</th>
            <th align="center">Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">TBD</td>
            <td align="center">Maximum Prefix ORF</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This extension to BGP does not change the underlying security issues in <xref target="RFC4271"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        TBD
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5291.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
